今天我们学习一些非同一般的东西
我们借助一些程序来理解更为深刻的理论
到目前为止，我们一直把程序看作可描述的机器
举个例子，这个幻灯片上有一个计算阶乘的程序
它不过就是一连串字符串描述的东西，如果想的话，你也可以用可能无限递归的机器的布线图来表示
我们只消看一点就明白程序是怎么回事
这种记法很简洁，这句描述的是，如果n是0，结果就是1
这里n输入机器，如果是0，就控制这个开关转到输出为1的方向
否则，开关就转到输出为 n乘以n-1的阶乘 的方向
下面计算的是n乘以n-1的阶乘，当n不是0的时候，开关就转到这个方向，输出这部分的计算
当然，这个机器可能是有无数个部件，因为factorial内部又调用了factorial，因此我们也不知道递归的深度是多少
这就是程序的记法所告诉我们的
字符串可以描述程序，如果你想，用布线图表示也是可以的
事实上，很多人都对我说过，说编程语言和这种图形很相似
不过我不认为用图形表示会有很多优势
一个缺点就是表示出来需要占用很大的平面空间，所以就很难一次性表示很大的程序，而且编辑修改起来也不方便
但是不管怎样，有一个叫做“通用机”的机器还是很值得我们注意的
我们再来看第二张幻灯片，这个特殊的机器名为eval
这个eval也就是今天要讲的
它非常简单
甚至在黑板这么小的空间里都能把它写出来
要注意的是，eval的输入比较特殊，它以对其它机器的描述作为输入
这里它以一个计算阶乘的机器的布线图描述作为输入
这样一来，eval变成了计算阶乘机器的模拟器，对eval输入6，得到阶乘结果720
这种机器非同一般
最让人吃惊的是只消在黑板这么小的空间内就可以描述完它
我们可以类比着来看，假设在现实里的模拟电路中，有这样一种通用的机器，它以电路设计图纸为输入，像是低通滤波器、 单极点低通滤波器之类的
你可以这样想像，用这个机器进行扫描输出 -- 扫描线应该可以描述出通用机在模拟的这个机器 -- 使用响应特定频率的滤波电路图的通用机模拟的效果应该和真实的滤波器达到的效果一样
这种机器很难制造出来，我肯定也不能只在黑板这么大的空间就具体的表述出它
所以说，今天是我们见证奇迹的时刻
我们将会见证，在黑板上，我就可以“制造”出通用机
除了部分事情以外，它其实非常简单
我们也逐渐触碰到活在计算机中真正的神灵
这里务必要保持足够的尊敬，所以我特地穿上西服外套，你们应该从没见我穿过
我想我还得戴上一顶合适的帽子
开讲前再给大家提个醒 -- 40岁以下以及还没有几个孩子的人要小心了
如果你真的受不了，可以选择离开 因为一会儿要发生的事情非常神秘，可能使你的思想异常混乱
好了，无论如何，我还是要向你们写一下Lisp的求值程序
求值程序并不复杂
很像我们以前见到过的程序
这也是它令人吃惊的地方
现在我开始写这个程序，叫做eval
它是一个接受两个参数的过程，exp是表达式，env是表达式执行的环境
和很多有趣的过程一样，过程内部按情况分析
但是在我开始之前，我还想告诉你们一些其它的
这里的这个程序非常丑陋、混乱、令人作呕，并不是一种专业的写法
它用具体的语法写就，也就是说我们用很多CAR CDR之类，我之前告诉过你们这样写并不好
在这里是故意这样来写的，因为我想使其娇小，简洁，达到可以写在黑板上的规模
我就不像平时那样使用很多很长的命名了
就用CAR CDR，很简洁
这算是一种权衡
我不希望你们这样来写程序
这里单纯地想达到一种简洁的效果
因此你们读起来可能有些费力，我尽量写的清楚
这个求值器比较完整，但是并不完全，我就不写define和assignment的部分了，不是它们不重要，而是出于一些数学上的原因，再说黑板地方也不大
但是，我们怎么做呢？
这里需要做一个分配，把表达式分类
这就是现在要做的
这里的表达式应该是什么？
我们先来看几种表达式
表达式数字3
要怎么做？
我有很多选择，但是我马上想到，它就应该是数字3
这就是我要的
这个足够简单
那就意味着，如果表达式是数字，表达式本身就应该是求值结果
表达式还可能是符号
比如x n eval number之类
它们意味着什么？
它们是一类代表其它事物的事物
也就是我们语言中所谓的变量
因此，假如这有一个x，求值结果应该是它代表的那个值，我随便写一个3
又假如符号是car
这时候来求值，结果应该是一个过程，具体内部可能是机器码或是别的，不过这里我们并不需要关心
到这是还是相对简单的
我还是想把符号求值的具体部分交给别人来写
假如表达式是符号，就执行(lookup exp env)，得到表达式在当前环境的结果
这里的环境就相当于一本字典，根据符号名字就可以查找到相应的值
就这么简单
env在这里到底是什么？
稍后我们再谈这个
其实并不难
就是一个融合了多种排序的表结构
可以简单理解为它就是一个表，lookup过程可以查找这个表
好的，接下来，下一种可能 -- 表达式可能是一些不是数字的常数，比如'foo
这里方便起见，我把它转化为语法上等同的形式(quote foo)
求值器并不处理引号，一个被引的表达式，无论它是什么，都是一个缩写，像是(quote foo)这种形式的缩写
这样我就可以依据表达式的car来判断表达式的类型了
因此这一部分也不难写
It's happening somewhere earlier in the reader or something.
如果表达式被引，求值结果是，这里(quote foo)的求值结果应该是foo自身
一个常量
也就是说求值结果是它自身
该怎么来写呢？
也就是列表的第二个部分了，应该是列表的CADR，所以这里我就写CADR
表达式还可能是什么类型呢？
还有lambda表达式，比如，(lambda (x) (+ x y))
这样的话，我就必须得有方法来表示过程，也就是lambda求值的结果
过程并不是lambda (x)表达式
表达式只是对过程的文字描述
相对地，我更希望执行过程的时候还要考虑环境的因素
所以这里我们需要一些类型标志
因为之后我们要凭借标志来区分哪些是过程，即lambda和一些原子元素求值的结果
这里考虑历史因素，我就用closure作为类型标志
现在来看看，哪些部分必不可少
我需要形参列表和过程体
也就是lambda的CDR，最后还有执行环境env
单纯的语言使用者肯定没见过像这样的，它只是内部对过程对象的一种表示方法吧
它包含了形参列表，过程体，执行环境，和表示自身为过程类型的标志
接下来写代码
如果表达式的CAR是'lambda，求值结果就是(list 'closure (cdr exp) env)
这样就实现了环境模型中的那些规则
对于从lambda构建一个过程是必不可少的
而且closure里的这个环境就是过程真正执行的时候查找自由变量的地方
所以这里应该有环境env
必须把环境作为过程对象的一部分
之后我们再来细看环境在其中的作用
下一种情况，条件表达式，(cond (p1 e1) (p2 e2) ...)
p是谓词，谓词求值结果非真即假，e是表达式，只有在谓词为真的时候才被求值
如果不介意，我暂时称其为一组子句
具体的求值过程写在别的地方
让别人来考虑具体求值的部分
这里继续写，如果(car exp)是'cond，然后就求值(cdr exp)
记得带上环境
好的，还有一种情况，比如(+ x 3)，一个操作符应用于操作数，它并不特殊
就是说，它不属于这里的特殊形式
上面写的这些都是特殊形式
还是再提一下，如果这里用数据导向的方式来写，会更加的专业
那样的话这里就不会是一系列的条件判断，数据导向会把这种按条件分配的过程表示的更为优雅
并且，我还可以在不改动代码的情况下添加新的条件判断
也可能那样会执行的更快，虽然有很多优势，这里我并不考虑那样来写
现在的目的是把握eval过程的全局
好吧，接着写
要怎么做呢？
这个(+ x 3)的例子里，我得做加法
那样的话我就得清楚 + 到底是什么
接着弄清楚 x 和 3 是什么
然后再把 + 的结果应用于 x 与 3 的结果
具体来写一下
(apply (eval (car exp) env)，(car exp)就是操作符的部分
执行(eval (car exp) env)就得到操作符的结果
我还得求值操作数来得到具体参数
执行evlist来求值操作数
(evlist (cdr exp) env)，这个evlist稍后细讲
你现在看到的就是一个完整的求值器
它针对表达式的类型分情况处理，表达式可以是一个完整的程序或者简单表达式的组合
不过我们还有些过程没有被定义
接下来就看这些未定义的部分
evcond稍后再说
我得定义apply
还有evlist，lookup
我看看，没别的了吧？
剩下的就是一些简单基本的东西了
当然，这里可以写很多特殊形式，但是对于一个语言来说无疑很糟糕
那会让语言变得很复杂
保留字就不该比你能记住几个手指脚指的数目还多
看到有些语言的保留字有上百个，我都不知道该说什么
特殊形式也就是所谓定义保留字的地方
好的，接下来，我们来看第二个核心的部分，apply
它还做些什么呢？
apply主要是将过程应用于实际参数，这里所说的是过程和参数的符号求值的结果，而不是过程和参数的符号
所以我们定义apply过程，接受两个参数分别代表将应用的过程和这个过程的参数列表
具体怎么来写呢？
其实并不复杂
分两种情况就够了
如果这个过程是基本过程 -- 我不知道这个谓词具体是根据什么来判断的
可能原理就像我们用'closure标志来表示组合结构的类型一样，我想可能是这样
但是深究这个谓词并不必要，事实上你可能已经知道或是演绎过，我们并不需要任何基本过程
我们没有基本过程只用lambda也照样可以正常计算
但是有它们总归方便点儿
接下来就是精彩的部分了，我先不细讲
转到机器语言，执行apply-primop
加法就是这样运算的
执行加法指令
然而一门语言有趣的部分在于谓词是如何组合在一起的
我们接着往下看
另一种可能就是这是一个求值lambda得到的过程，一个复合过程
我们检测它的类型标志
如果是'closure，我就得求值这个过程体
这里我要将过程应用于其参数，也就是 将形参与实参绑定，添加入过程的运行环境，然后在此环境下对过程求值
这句话很长
但是描述的内容足够简单
一会儿可能会出现许多CAR CDR CADR ...
现在我先要得到过程体
过程体如何取出呢？
这一部分是CAR，剩下的是CDR部分
然后这里就是CADR，我看看，过程体就在整个过程第二部分的第二部分
也就是CADR的CADR，或者简写为CADADR
这里取整个过程的CADADR
为了在参数绑定后的新环境之中执行这个过程，我还得取到过程的形式参数，形参怎么取呢？
就是CDR的CAR，很混乱不是吗？
过程的CADR
绑定形参实参添加进环境中，环境也是随着过程被传递进来
也就是CDR的CDR的CAR，过程的CADDR
(bind (caadr proc) args (caddr proc)) 如果我有点强迫症，这里就会非常谨慎，我会在后面多加一个判断来处理错误情况，比如你对参数应用的是一个过程吗？
如果不是，这里就是未定义的过程类型
这里保持原样
下面加上else，如果出现错误情况
插个话，目前很多专业用途的系统中，内部的结构也与这类似，主要是分条件判断，分配处理不同情况
回到这里，我可能还会添加新的条件判断，比如这是编译过的代码吗？
这很重要
这样的话我就可以区分一段代码是我通过解释代码对lambda求值得到的结果还是通过编译器编译代码得到的结果
之后再讨论这个话题
又或许是我必须要执行的一段Frotran代码
如果这种可能发生了，记住，就在这里把情况加进去
事实上，我在写这个求值器的时候，有一个内在的假定即这是一种Lisp语言的实现方式，因为我大量使用了CAR CDR之类
CAR意味着操作符，CDR意味着操作数
在这种情形下，就可以想像已经存在了一个抽象的语法解析器，通过它我们就可以取到操作符操作数等等
在清楚了这个假定之后，你完全可以用ALGOL再来实现这个求值器
写完apply之后，发现又引入了一些未定义的过程
我先不操心这两个，下面这个BIND还是挺有意思的
现在我们来快速过一遍，结束这一部分
只剩下两块黑板了，因此它们加起来代码并不多
不过代码还得精心剪裁一番才可以全部放的进黑板
嗯，还剩下点什么？
我们得定义那边的evlist
evlist不过是遍历一串操作数生成实际参数
但是还是写出来看看
还要把它写出来是为了一个神秘的原因，就是我想要求值器简单到可以求值自身
这一点还是有点重要的
现在我就把它完全写在这里
看，我完全不用操心是否传递入的参数是一个过程
求值器并不会真正使用到它们
求值器也不会生成一个是过程的值
因此，如果有一个不同的，和scheme非常相似的语言，它也可以像scheme一样求值比如使用过程参数，返回过程为值，允许过程作为数据
值得注意的是，如果我对ALGOL语言求值，也可以使用这个求值器，尽管ALGOL并不允许过程作为返回值
因为这个解释器并没有对这些事情做过什么假定
事实上，如果被求值的语言真的被限定了不能做这做那，没关系，只能算它们没有使用到这些高级功能
这也是为什么我可以将求值器组织的如此简单
这几乎是所有现存语言求值器的核心
回到这个定义上来
evlise，它是什么呢？
这个过程也有两个参数，l和env，l是所有参数的列表，如果l为空，就返回一个空列表，否则就先在环境中求值第一个参数
求值第一个参数之后，我想要在当前环境递归evlist求值CDR部分，和第一个求值结果连接为列表
闭合括号evlist cons else cond lambda define，还有一个过程我也想写在这里
它是整件事的关键部分
还要深入一个层次
条件式 -- 在剩下的过程中，条件式是唯一一个非常重要的过程
除了这个，我们还有lookup bind的过程要讨论
但是在这个讨论事情相对具体的层次上，下一个重要的事就是你如何处理条件式
这里，条件式具体要怎么写？
它是一个过程，参数是一串子句和环境
它做些什么呢？
如果这里没有子句，我得有一个返回值
可能是一个错误
假设它遍历完了所有条件，都没有符合的，接下来发生什么还真不好说
这完全取决于我，作为一个程序员可以选择应该怎么处理
对我来说实在太方便了，现在我写一个空列表作为返回值，完全无碍
如是有些人倾向于错误检测，他们可以在这里写点别的
下面的更有意思
这里有一系列的子句，每个子句都是一个列表，假如我遇到一个else子句，子句的谓词部分应该是子句的CAAR
所有子句中第一个子句的第一个部分
如果是else，就意味着整个条件式的结果就是执行这个else子句中表达式的结果
所以接着对CADAR部分在当前环境下求值，就是第一个子句的第二个部分
下一种可能性更有意思
如果不是else子句，而且子句的谓词结果是false -- 我们接着写
在当前环境下求值子句的谓词部分，如果是false，这就意味着还得接着判断下面的子句
第一个就扔掉不管了
我们还得在当前环境下，继续递归evcond循环子句的CDR部分
又或者，我遇到了一个真子句，即求值子句的谓词部分结果为真
条件式就要到尾声了
非常近了
把这一部分结束
回到全局再看一遍求值器，你已经对它有一个完整的把握了
接着来看一张幻灯片
bind的定义
bind在环境中添加新的绑定
我们这里先依照环境的数据结构构造一个frame
环境就是由一系列的frame组成的
所以对于环境来说，我把一个新的frame和环境连接在一起就构成了新的环境，新的frame是由pair-up对形参与实参进行绑定得到的结果
环境也就是一个列表而已，构造一个新frame元素，添加入列表就构成了新环境
其实pair-up非常简单
对于一个变量的列表和一个值的列表，两个列表中元素个数应该相同
如果不同，就是实参的数目不对了
假如值遍历完了，还剩下有变量，说明实参给少了
如果没有遇到错误，即变量和值是可以对上号的，就应该用第一个变量和第一个值构造一个序对，和pair-up对两列表CDR的求值结果相连接
lookup也简单
假使我要在环境中查找一个变量，环境是空的，这个变量就是未绑定的
否则，就调用一个新的过程来从环境的第一个frame开始查找变量
因为环境不是空的，所以一定有第一个frame
所以我就在第一个frame中查找
找到的序对也就是这里的vcell
如果vcell为空，我就需要在环境中剩下的frame中查找
vcell为空意味着当前frame没有找到变量
如果没有找到，assq就会返回空值
如果找到了，值就应该是vcell的CDR部分，因为vcell是一个变量和值的序对
因此CDR就取到了值
assq这个过程你们之前见过
assq取一个符号和一系列序对的列表，如果列表为空，变返回'()
如果符号等于列表中第一个 -- 这里写错了
应该是CAAR，大家注意了
就是这里，看见了吗？
如果符号等于列表的CAAR，然后就取列表的第一个序对元素作为返回值，这就是我们要找的绑定；如果符号与之不相同，就在剩下的列表中继续查找。很抱歉刚才幻灯片上面写错了
到现在为止，你们也已看到了全貌
虽然用很难看的编程方式书写出来，但是仍然不能掩盖它的美丽与优雅，这正是语言的核心所在
这样优美的程序，我们可以多看一会儿[骗人啊，说好的只写一黑板呢，又刷出N张幻灯片啊]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
大家有什么问题吗？
没有的话就休息一会儿吧
[MUSIC PLAYING]
OK, now we're just going to do a little bit of practice understanding what it is we've just shown you.
What we're going to do is go through, in detail, an evaluation by informally substituting through the interpreter.
And since we have no assignments or definitions in this interpreter, we have no possible side effects, and so the we can do substitution with impunity and not worry about results.
So the particular problem I'd like to look at is it an interesting one.
It's the evaluation of quote, open, open, open, lambda of x, lambda of y plus x y, lambda, lambda, applied to three, applied to four, in some global environment which I'll call e0.
So what we have here is a procedure of one argument x, which produces as its value a procedure of one argument y, which adds x to y.
We are applying the procedure of one argument x to three.
So x should become three.
And the result of that should be procedure of one argument y, which will then apply to 4.
And there is a very simple case, they will then add those results.
And now in order to do that, I want to make a very simple environment model.
And at this point, you should already have in your mind the environments that this produces.
But we're going to start out with a global environment, which I'll call e0, which is that.
And it's going to have in it things, definitions for plus, and times, and-- using Greek letters, isn't that interesting, for the objects-- and minus, and quotient, and CAR, and CDR, and CONS, and EQ, and everything else you might imagine in a global environment.
It's got something there for each of those things, something the machine is born with, that's e0.
Now what does it mean to do this evaluation?
Well, we go through the set of special forms. First of all, this is not a number.
This is not a symbol.
Gee, it's not a quoted expression.
This is a quoted expression, but that's not what I interested in.
The question is, whether or not the thing which is quoted is quoted expression?
I'm evaluating an expression.
This just says it's this particular expression.
This is not a quoted expression.
It's not a thing that begins with lambda.
It's not a thing that begins with COND.
Therefore, it's an application of its of an operated operands.
It's a combination.
The combination thus has this as the operator and this is the operands.
Well, that means that what I'm going to do is transform this into apply of eval, of quote, open, open lambda of x, lambda of y-- I'm evaluating the operator-- plus x y, in the environment, also e0, with the operands that I'm going to apply this to, the arguments being the result of EVLIST, the list containing four, fin e0.
I'm using this funny notation here for e0 because this should be that environment.
I haven't a name for it, because I have no environment to name it in.
So this is just a representation of what would be a quoted expression, if you will.
The data structure, which is the environment, goes there.
Well, that's what we're seeing here.
Well in order to do this, I have to do this, and I have to do that.
Well this one's easy, so why don't we do that one first.
This turns into apply of eval-- just copying something now.
Most of the substitution rule is copying.
So I'm going to not say the words when I copy, because it's faster.
And then the EVLIST is going to turn into a cons, of eval, of four, in e0--  because it was not an empty list-- onto the result of EVLISTing, on the empty list, in e0.
And I'm going to start leaving out steps soon, because it's going to get boring.
But this is basically the same thing as apply, of eval--  I'm going to keep doing this-- the lambda of x, the lambda of y, plus xy, 3, close, e0.
I'm a pretty good machine.
Well, eval of four, that's meets the question, is it a number.
So that's cons, cons of 4.
And EVLIST of the empty list is the empty list, so that's this.
And that's very simple to understand, because that means the list containing four itself.
So this is nothing more than apply of eval, quote, open, open, lambda of x, lambda of y, plus x y, three applied to, e0, applied to the list four-- bang.
So that's that step.
Now let's look at the next, more interesting thing.
What do I do to evaluate that?
Evaluating this means I have to evaluate-- Well, it's not.
It's nothing but an application.
It's not one of the special things.
If the application of this operator, which we see here-- here's the operator-- applied to this operands, that combination.
But we know how to do that, because that's the last case of the conditional.
So substituting in for this evaluation, it's apply of eval of the operator in the EVLIST of the operands.
Well, it's apply, of apply, of eval, of quote, open, lambda of x, lambda of y, plus x y, lambda, lambda, in environment e0.
I'm going to short circuit the evaluation of the operands , because they're the same as they were before.
I got a list containing three, apply that, and apply that to four.
Well let's see.
Eval of a lambda expression produces a procedure object.
So this is apply, of apply, of the procedure object closure, which contains the body of the procedure, x, which is lambda-- which binds x [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
the internals of the body, it returns the procedure of one argument y, which adds x to y.
Environment e0 is now captured in it, because this was evaluated with respect to e0.
e0 is part now of the closure object.
Apply that to open, three, close, apply, to open, 4, close, apply.
So going from this step to this step meant that I made up a procedure object which captured in it e0 as part of the procedure object.
Now, we're going to pass those to apply.
We have to apply this procedure to that set of arguments.
Well, but that procedure is not primitive.
It's, in fact, a thing which has got the tag closure, and, therefore, what we have to do is do a bind.
We have to bind.
A new environment is made at this point, which has as its parent environment the one over here, e0, that environment.
And we'll call this one, e1.
Now what's bound in there?
x is bound to three.
So I have x equal three.
That's what's in there.
And we'll call that e1.
So what this transforms into is an eval of the body of this, which is this, the body of that procedure, in the environment that you just saw.
So that's an apply, of eval, quote, open, lambda of y, plus x y-- the body--  in e1.
And apply the result of that to four, open, close, 4-- list of arguments.
Well, that's sensible enough because evaluating a lambda, I know what to do.
That means I apply, the procedure which is closure, binds one argument y, adds x to y, with e1 captured in it.
And you should really see this.
I somehow manufactured a closure.
I should've put this here.
There was one over here too.
Well, there's one here now.
I've captured e1, and this is the procedure of one argument y, whatever this is.
That's what that is there, that closure.
I'm going to apply that to four.
Well, that's easy enough.
That means I have to make a new environment by copying this pointer, which was the pointer of the procedure, which binds y equal 4 with that environment.
And here's my new environment, which I'll call e2.
And, of course, this application then is evaluate the body in e2.
So this is eval, the body, which is plus x y, in the environment e2.
But this is an application, so this is the apply, of eval, plus in e2, an EVLIST, quote, open, x y, in e2.
Well, but let's see.
That is apply, the object which is a result of that and plus.
So here we are in e2, plus is not here, it's not here, oh, yes, but's here as some primitive operator.
So it's the primitive operator for addition.
Apply that to the result of evaluating x and y in e2.
But we can see that x is three and y is four.
So that's a three and four, here.
And that magically produces for me a seven.
I wanted to go through this so you would see, essentially, one important ingredient, which is what's being passed around, and who owns what, and what his job is.
So what do we have here?
We have eval, and we have apply, the two main players.
And there is a big loop the goes around like this.
Which is eval produces a procedure and arguments for apply.
Now some things eval could do by itself.
Those are little self things here.
They're not interesting.
Also eval evaluates all of the arguments, one after another.
That's not very interesting.
Apply can apply some procedures like plus, not very interesting.
However, if apply can't apply a procedure like plus, it produces an expression and environment for eval.
The procedural arguments wrap up essentially the state of a computation and, certainly, the expression of environment.
And so what we're actually going to do next is not the complete state, because it doesn't say who wants the answers.
But what we're going to do-- it's always got something like an expression of environment or procedure and arguments as the main loop that we're going around.
There are minor little sub loops like eval through EVLIST, or eval through evcond, or apply through a primitive apply.
But they're not the essential things.
So that's what I wanted you to see.
Are there any questions?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: I'm trying to understand how x got down to three instead of four.
At the early part of the-- PROFESSOR: Here.
You want to know how x got down to three?
AUDIENCE: Because x is the outer procedure, and x and y are the inner procedure.
PROFESSOR: Fine.
Well, I was very careful and mechanical.
First of all, I should write those procedures again for you, pretty printed.
First order of business, because you're probably not reading them well.
So I have here that procedure of-- was it x over there-- which is-- value of that procedure of y, which adds x to y, lambda, lambda, applied that to three, takes the result of that, and applied that to four.
Is that not what I wrote?
Now, you should immediately see that here is an application-- let me get a white piece of chalk-- here is an application, a combination.
That combination has this as the operator and this as the operand.
The three is going in for the x here.
The result of this is a procedure of one argument y, which gets applied to four.
So you just weren't reading the expression right.
The way you see that over here is that here I have the actual procedure object, x.
It's getting applied to three, the list containing three.
What I'm left over with is something which gets applied to four.
Are there any other questions?
Time for our next small break then.
Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Let's see, at this point, you should be getting the feeling, what's this nonsense this Sussman character is feeding me?
There's an awful lot of strange nonsense here.
After all, he purported to explain to me Lisp, and he wrote me a Lisp program on the blackboard.
The Lisp program was intended to be interpreted for Lisp, but you need a Lisp interpreter in order to understand that program.
How could that program have told me anything there is to be known about Lisp?
How is that not completely vacuous?
It's a very strange thing.
Does it tell me anything at all?
Well, you see, the whole thing is sort of like these Escher's hands that we see on this slide.
Yes, eval and apply each sort of draw each other and construct the real thing, which can sit out and draw itself.
Escher was a very brilliant man, he just didn't know the names of these spirits.
Well, I'm going to do now, is I'm going to try to convince you that both this mean something, and, as a aside, I'm going to show you why you don't need definitions.
Just turns out that that sort of falls out, why definitions are not essential in a mathematical sense for doing all the things we need to do for computing.
Well, let's see here.
Consider the following small program, what does it mean?
This is a program for computing exponentials.
The exponential of x to the nth power is if--  and is zero, then the result is one.
Otherwise, I want the product of x and the result of exponentiating x to the n minus one power.
I think I got it right.
Now this is a recursive definition.
It's a definition of the exponentiation procedure in terms of itself.
And, as it has been mentioned before, your high school geometry teacher probably gave you a hard time about things like that.
Was that justified?
Why does this self referential definition make any sense?
Well, first of all, I'm going to convince you that your high school geometry teacher was I telling you nonsense.
Consider the following set of definitions here.
x plus y equals three, and x minus y equal one.
Well, gee, this tells you x in terms of y, and this one tells you y in terms of x, presumably.
And yet this happens to have a unique solution in x and y.
However, I could also write two x plus two y is six.
These two equations have an infinite number solutions.
And I could write you, for example, x minus y equal 2, and these two equations have no solutions.
Well, I have here three sets of simultaneous linear equations, this set, this set, and this set.
But they have different numbers of solutions.
The number of solutions is not in the form of the equations.
They all three sets have the same form.
The number of solutions is in the content.
I can't tell by looking at the form of a definition whether it makes sense, only by its detailed content.
What are the coefficients, for example, in the case of linear equations?
So I shouldn't expect to be able to tell looking at something like this, from some simple things like, oh yes, EXPT is the solution of this recursion equation.
Expt is the procedure which if substituted in here, gives me EXPT back.
I can't tell, looking at this form, whether or not there's a single, unique solution for EXPT, an infinite number of solutions, or no solutions.
It's got to be how it counts and things like that, the details.
And it's harder in programming than linear algebra.
There aren't too many theorems about it in programming.
Well, I want to rewrite these equations a little bit, these over here.
Because what we're investigating is equations like this.
But I want to play a little with equations like this that we understand, just so we get some insight into this kind of question.
We could rewrite our equations here, say these two, the ones that are interesting, as x equals three minus y, and y equals x minus one.
What do we call this transformation?
This is a linear transformation, t.
Then what we're getting here is an equation x y equals t of x y.
What am I looking for?
I'm looking for a fixed point of t.
The solution is a fixed point of t.
So the methods we should have for looking for solutions to equations, if I can do it by fixed points, might be applicable.
If I have a means of finding a solution to an equations by fixed points-- just, might not work-- but it might be applicable to investigating solutions of equations like this.
But what I want you to feel is that this is an equation.
It's an expression with several instances of various names which puts a constraint on the name, saying what that name could have as its value, rather than some sort of mechanical process of substitution right now.
This is an equation which I'm going to try to solve.
Well, let's play around and solve it.
First of all, I want to write down the function which corresponds to t.
First I want to write down the function which corresponds to t whose fixed point is the answer to this question.
Well, let's consider the following procedure f.
I claim it computes that function.
f is that procedure of one argument g, which is that procedure of two arguments x and n.
Which have the property that if n is zero, then the result is one, otherwise, the result is the product of x and g, applied to x, and minus n1.
g, times, else, COND, lambda, lambda--  Here f is a procedure, which if I had a solution to that equation, if I had a good exponentiation procedure, and I applied f to that procedure, then the result would be a good exponentiation procedure.
Because, what does it do?
Well, all it is is exposing g were a good exponentiation procedure, well then this would produce, as its value, a procedure to arguments x and n, such that if n were 0, the result would be one, which is certainly true of exponentiation.
Otherwise, it will be the result of multiplying x by the exponentiation procedure given to me with x and n minus one as arguments.
So if this computed the correct exponentiation for n minus one, then this would be the correct exponentiation for exponent n, so this would have been the right exponentiation procedure.
So what I really want to say here is E-X-P-T is a fixed point of f.
Now our problem is there might be more than one fixed point.
There might be no fixed points.
I have to go hunting for the fixed points.
Got to solve this equation.
Well there are various ways to hunt for fixed points.
Of course, the one we played with at the beginning of this term worked for cosine.
Go into radians mode on your calculator and push cosine, and just keep doing it, and you get to some number which is about 0.73 or 0.74.
I can't remember which.
By iterating a function, whose fixed point I'm searching for, it is sometimes the case that that function will converge in producing the fixed point.
I think we luck out in this case, so let's look for it.
Let's look at this slide.
Consider the following sequence of procedures.
e0 over here is the procedure which does nothing at all.
It's the procedure which produces an error for any arguments you give it.
It's basically useless.
Well, however, I can make an approximation.
Let's consider it the worst possible approximation to exponentiation, because it does nothing.
Well, supposing I substituted e0 for g by calling f, as you see over here on e0.
So you see over here, have e0 there.
Then gee, what's e1?
e1 is a procedure which exponentiate things to the 0th power, with no trouble.
It gets the right answer, anything to the zero is one, and it makes an error on anything else.
Well, now what if I take e1 and I substitute if for g by calling f on e1?
Oh gosh, I have here a procedure of two arguments.
Now remember e1 was appropriate for taking exponentiations of 0, for raising to the 0 exponent.
So here, is n is 0, the result is one, so this guy is good for that too.
However, I can use something for raising to the 0th power to multiply it by x to raise something to the first power.
So e2 is good for both power 0 and one.
And e3 is constructed from e2 in the same way.
And e3, of course, by the same argument is good for powers 0, one, and two.
And so I will assert for you, without proof, because the proof is horribly difficult.
And that's the sort of thing that people called denotational semanticists do.
This great idea was invented by Scott and Strachey.
They're very famous mathematician types who invented the interpretation for these programs that we have that I'm talking to you about right now.
And they proved, by topology that there is such a fixed point in the cases that we want.
But the assertion is E-X-P-T is limit as n goes to infinity of em.
and And that we've constructed this by the following way.
--is Well, it's f of, f of, f of, f of, f of-- f applied to anything at all.
It didn't matter what that was, because, in fact, this always produces an error.
Applied to this--  That's by infinite nesting of f's.
So now my problem is to make some infinite things.
We need some infinite things.
How am I going to nest up an f an infinite number of times?
I'd better construct this.
Well, I don't know.
How would I make an infinite loop at all?
Let's take a very simple infinite loop, the simplest infinite loop imaginable.
If I were to take that procedure of one argument x which applies x to x and apply that to the procedure of one argument x which applies x to x, then this is an infinite loop.
The reason why this is an infinite loop is as follows.
The way I understand this is I substitute the argument for the formal parameter in the body.
But if I do that, I take for each of these x's, I substitute one of these, making a copy of the original expression I just started with, the simplest infinite loop.
Now I want to tell you about a particular operator which is constructed by a perturbation from this infinite loop.
I'll call it y.
This is called Curry's Paradoxical Combinator of y after a fellow by the name of Curry, who was a logician of the 1930s also.
And if I have a procedure of one argument f, what's it going to have in it?
It's going to have a kind of infinite loop in it, which is that procedure of one argument x which applies f to x of x, applied to that procedure of one argument x, which applies f to f of x.
Now what's this do?
Suppose we apply y to F. Well, that's easy enough.
That's this capital F over here.
Well, the easiest thing to say there is, I substitute F for here.
So that's going to give me, basically-- because then I'm going to substitute this for x in here.
Let me actually do it in steps, so you can see it completely.
I'm going to be very careful.
This is open, open, lambda of x , capital F, x, x, applied to itself, F of x of x.
Substituting this for this in here, this is F applied to-- what is it-- substituting this in here, open, open, lambda of x, F, of x and x, applied to lambda of x, F of x of x, F, lambda, pair, F.
Oh, but what is this?
This thing over here that I just computed, is this thing over here.
But I just wrapped another F around it.
So by applying y to F, I make an infinite series of F's.
If I just let this run forever, I'll just keep making more and more F's outside.
I ran an infinite loop which is useless, but it doesn't matter that the inside is useless.
So y of F is F applied to y of F. So y is a magical thing which, when applied to some function, produces the object which is the fixed point of that function, if it exists, and if this all works.
Because, indeed, if I take y of F and put it into F, I get y of F out.
Now I want you to think this in terms of the eval-apply interpreter for a bit.
I wrote down a whole bunch of recursion equations out there.
They're simultaneous in the same way these are simultaneous equations.
Exponentiation was not a simultaneous equation.
It was only one variable I was looking for a meaning for.
But what Lisp is is the fixed point of the process which says, if I knew what Lisp was and substituted it in for eval, and apply, and so on, on the right hand sides of all those recursion equations, then if it was a real good Lisp, is a real one, then the left hand side would also be Lisp.
So I made sense of that definition.
Now whether or not there's an answer isn't so obvious.
I can't attack that.
Now these arguments that I'm giving you now are quite dangerous.
Let's look over here.
These are limit arguments.
We're talking about limits, and it's really calculus, or topology, or something like that, a kind of analysis.
Now here's an argument that you all believe.
And I want to make sure you realize that I could be bullshitting you.
What is this?
u is the sum of 1/2, 1/4, and 1/8, and so on, the sum of a geometric series.
And, of course, I could play a game here.
u minus one is 1/2, plus 1/4, plus 1/8, and so on.
What I could do here-- oops.
There is a parentheses error here.
But I can put here two times u minus one is one plus 1/2, plus 1/4, plus 1/8.
Can I fix that?
Yes, well.
But that gives me back two times u minus one is u, therefore, we conclude that u is two.
And this actually is true.
There's no problem like that.
But supposing I did something different.
Supposing I start up with something which manifestly has no sum.
v is one, plus two, plus four, plus 8, plus dot, dot, dot.
Well, v minus one is surely two, plus four, plus eight, plus dot, dot, dot.
v minus one over two, gee, that looks like v again.
From that I should be able to conclude that-- that's also wrong, apparently.
v equals minus one.
That should be a minus one.
And that's certainly a false conclusion.
So when you play with limits, arguments that may work in one case they may not work in some other case.
You have to be very careful.
The arguments have to be well formed.
And I don't know, in general, what the story is about arguments like this.
We can read a pile of topology and find out.
But, surely, at least you understand now, why it might be some meaning to the things we've been writing on the blackboard.
And you understand what that might mean.
So, I suppose, it's almost about time for you to merit being made a member of the grand recursive order of lambda calculus hackers.
This is the badge.
Because you now understand, for example, what it says at the very top, y F equals F y F. Thank you.
Are there any questions?
Yes, Lev.
AUDIENCE: With this, it seems that then there's no need to define, as you imply, to just remember a value, to apply it later.
Defines were kind of a side-effect it seemed in the language.
[INTERPOSING]
are order dependent.
Does this eliminate the side-effect from the [INTERPOSING]
PROFESSOR: The answer is, this is not the way these things were implemented.
Define, indeed is implemented as an operation that actually modifies an environment structure, changes the frame that the define is executed in.
And there are many reasons for that, but a lot of this has to do with making an interactive system.
What this is saying is that if you've made a system, and you know you're not going to do any debugging or anything like that, and you know everything there is all at once, and you want to say, what is the meaning of a final set of equations?
This gives you a meaning for it.
But in order to make an interactive system, where you can change the meaning of one thing without changing everything else, incrementally, you can't do that by implementing it this way.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: Another question on your danger slide.
It seemed that the two examples that you gave had to do with convergence and non-convergence?
And that may or may not have something to do with function theory in a way which would lead you to think of it in terms of linear systems, or non-linear systems. How does this convergence relate to being able to see a priori what properties of that might be violated?
PROFESSOR: I don't know.
The answer is, I don't know under what circumstances.
I don't know how to translate that into less than an hour of talk more.
What are the conditions under which, for which we know that these things converge?
And v, all that was telling you that arguments that are based on convergence are flaky if you don't know the convergence beforehand.
You can make wrong arguments.
You can make deductions, as if you know the answer, and not be stopped somewhere by some obvious contradiction.
AUDIENCE: So can we say then that if F is a convergent mathematical expression, then the recursion property can be-- PROFESSOR: Well, I think there's a technical kind of F, there is a technical description of those F's that have the property that when you iteratively apply them like this, you converge.
Things that are monotonic, and continuous, and I forgot what else.
There is a whole bunch of little conditions like that which have this property.
Now the real problem is deducing from looking at the F, its definition here, whether not it has those properties, and that's very hard.
The properties are easy.
You can write them down.
You can look in a book by Joe Stoy.
It's a great book-- Stoy.
It's called, The Scott-Strachey Method of Denotational Semantics, and it's by Joe Stoy, MIT Press.
And he works out all this in great detail, enough to horrify you.
But it really is readable.
OK, well, thank you.
Time for the bigger break, I suppose.